Şu dağın ardında bir taş olaydım.
I wish I were a stone behind that mountain.
Gelene gidene yoldaş olaydım.
I wish I were a companion to everyone passing by.
Şu dağın ardında bir taş olaydım.
I wish I were a stone behind that mountain.
Gelene gidene yoldaş olaydım.
I wish I were a companion to everyone passing by.
Köprüden geçtim, köprü kırıldı.
I crossed the bridge, the bridge broke.
Köprüden indim, köprü yıkıldı.
I went down from the bridge, the bridge collapsed.
Anasız babasız boynum büküldü.
Motherless and fatherless, my neck was bowed.
Ben bir öksüzdüm, ortada kaldım.
I was an orphan, I was left all alone.
مرساوا، قرية سورية جميلة تتبع ناحية شران منطقة عفرين في ريف
حلب الشمالي.
Mersawa, a beautiful Syrian village belonging to the Sheran
sub-district, Afrin district, in the northern countryside of
Aleppo.
وهي تقع إلى الشمال من شران بـ 20 كيلومتراً، وإلى الشمال
الشرقي من مدينة عفرين بـ 40 كيلومتراً،
It is located 20 kilometers north of Sheran, and 40
kilometers northeast of the city of Afrin,
وإلى الشمال من مدينة حلب بـ 90 كيلومتراً، وشمال قلعة النبي
هوري بـ 3 كيلومترات.
and 90 kilometers north of the city of Aleppo, and 3
kilometers north of the Nebi Houri Castle.
إلى الشمال منها تقع الحدود التركية السورية، وأما جنوبها فتقع
قرية النبي هوري،
To its north lie the Turkish-Syrian borders, while to its
south is the village of Nebi Houri,
وشرقاً قرية شيلتاح، وأما جنوباً فقرية عبودان.
to the east the village of Shiltah, and also to the south
the village of Aboudan.
سكانها الأصليون من العرب السوريين الذين ينتمون إلى عشيرتي
البوبنا والمجادمة،
Its original inhabitants are Syrian Arabs belonging to the
Boubanna and Majadima tribes,
ومن الأكراد السوريين الذين ينتمون إلى عشيرة أومكي.
and Syrian Kurds belonging to the Omeki tribe.
يسكن فيها حالياً قرابة 130 عائلة من سكانها الأصليين إضافة
إلى عوائل سورية مهجرة من مناطق مختلفة.
Currently, around 130 families of its original inhabitants
live there, in addition to displaced Syrian families from
different regions.
يشتهر أهلها بزراعة الزيتون والكروم والحبوب المختلفة
والخضروات، وبتربية الماعز والأغنام كون أن المنطقة جبلية.
Its people are famous for cultivating olives, vineyards,
various grains, and vegetables, and for raising goats and
sheep, since the area is mountainous.
يوجد في القرية مدرسة ابتدائية وحيدة أنشئت في أوائل سبعينيات
القرن الماضي.
There is a single primary school in the village, built in
the early 1970s.
يعبر من جهتها الجنوبية الغربية نهر الصابون سي أو الصافي،
ويصب في نهر عفرين.
The Sabun Suyu or Al-Safi river crosses its southwestern
side and flows into the Afrin River.
يتميز أهلها بالطبيعة الريفية الزراعية والبساطة وحب الضيف
والكرم.
Its people are characterized by their rural, agricultural
nature, simplicity, hospitality, and generosity.
بهالضيعة الصغيرة، في معمرة كبيرة، هي الحجة دلّي هلال، يلي
عمرها بيتجاوز الـ 135 سنة،
In this small village, there is an elderly woman, Hajja
Dalli Hilal, who is over 135 years old,
وبهالحالة بتكون من أكبر المعمرين في العالم،
and in this case, she would be one of the oldest people in
the world,
رغم إنو يعني بطاقة تسجيلها أو هويتها السورية بتقول إنو هي
أصغر من هيك،
although her registration card or Syrian ID says she is
younger than that,
لكن البعض عم يقول إنو هي تسجلت وعمرها كان كثير كبير، يعني
بالـ 40 سنة.
but some say that she was registered when she was already
very old, around 40 years old.
رح نكون معكم بزيارة لبيت الحجة دلّي هلال لنتعرف عليها، على
شخصيتها، كيف بتقضي يومياتها، علاقتها بالآخرين،
We will be with you on a visit to Hajja Dalli Hilal's house
to get to know her, her personality, how she spends her
days, her relationship with others,
واليوم كيف صحتها وأوضاعها، تابعونا.
and how her health and situation are today. Stay with us.
يا رب... أبو شيخو!
Oh Lord... Abu Sheikho!
يا هلا أهلاً وسهلاً أستاذ مصطفى على راسي، أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome, welcome Mr. Mustafa, on my head, welcome.
شلونك؟ شلون صحتك؟ والدتك؟
How are you? How is your health? Is this your mother?
إي هي والدتي. أهلاً وسهلاً.
Yes, she is my mother. Welcome.
شلونك؟
How are you?
الحمد لله من الله، الحمد لله، أبو شيخو الحمد لله.
Thank God, from God, thank God, Abu Sheikho is fine, thank
God.
بدي الحجة.
I want to see the Hajja.
يا أهلاً وسهلاً، تفضل.
Welcome, please come in.
طبعاً والدتك بتصير ضرتها للحجة؟
Of course, your mother is the Hajja's co-wife?
إيوه، بتصير ضرتها إي.
Yes, she is her co-wife, yes.
أهلاً وسهلاً، شرفي.
Welcome, please come in.
يا أهلاً وسهلاً، تفضل يا أستاذ مصطفى. شرف.
Welcome, please come in Mr. Mustafa. Come in.
شلونك؟ تفضل. يا رب، يا الله.
How are you? Go ahead. Oh Lord, oh God.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
أستاذ مصطفى يسلم عليكي، يقولك السلام عليكم، هاد هو.
Mr. Mustafa is greeting you, he says peace be upon you, this
is him.
الله يسلمك يا أبوي، الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe, my son, may God keep you safe.
شلونك؟
How are you?
سلمتك يا أبوي، الله يندى عليك.
May you be safe my son, may God bless you.
شلون صحتك؟
How is your health?
الله يخلف عليك، ماشي الحال.
May God reward you, I'm doing alright.
يقول شلون صحتك؟
He says, how is your health?
الله يسلمك يا أبوي. الله يخلف عليك.
May God keep you safe my son. May God reward you.
أستاذ مصطفى بده يطلعكم على التلفزيون مباشرة يا يوم، يسلم
عليكي.
Mr. Mustafa wants to put you on TV directly, mother, he says
hello to you.
يقول شلون صحتك؟
He says, how is your health?
الله يسلمك، صحتي فلتت.
May God keep you safe, my health is gone.
تعبانة يعني فرطت، من الله، ما ضل فيها خلص.
I am tired, I mean, I have withered, from God, there is
nothing left in me, it's over.
اي والله، تتمنى من الله تيجيها الموتة اليوم وتقول ما عم
تخلص... عرفت شلون؟
Yes, I swear, she wishes to God that death would come to her
today, and she says it's not ending... you know?
ما بتشوف الحجة؟
Can the Hajja not see?
والله نظرها خفيف يا أستاذ.
Honestly, her eyesight is weak, sir.
سمعها؟
Her hearing?
سمعها كمان ثقيل.
Her hearing is also heavy.
شقد عمرك يا أمي؟ شقد عمرك؟
How old are you, mother? How old are you?
عمري مية... مية وخمسة وثلاثين، ايش مدريني.
My age is one hundred... one hundred and thirty-five, how
should I know.
تقول 135.
She says 135.
ما شاء الله، شلون عرفتي إنو 135؟
Mashallah, how did you know it's 135?
شربوني مية... مية الصحة شربوني من هالشي، أعيش يعني...
They made me drink water... the water of health, they made
me drink it, that's why I live this long...
شربوكي مية السحر؟
Did they make you drink magic water?
لا، قال شربوني مية الحياة، قال بالمنام أجوني قال أنتِ بدك
تعيشي بعمر كذا.
No, she said they made me drink the water of life, she said
they came to me in a dream and said you will live to such an
age.
شفت بصحرا ما بيها حدا، ولاد اثنين بيها... شجيج من الوسطى
مشقوق،
I saw in a desert where there was no one, there were two
boys... a ravine split in the middle,
واحد بارك هين وواحد بارك هين، قال اشربي مية يا حجة، قلت إي
والله،
one was sitting here and one was sitting here, they said
drink water Hajja, I said yes by God,
انطيتني اشرب... جابوا لي طاسة عبوها شربت وما أعرف وين راحت
وين...
you gave me to drink... they brought me a bowl, filled it, I
drank, and I don't know where it went or where...
بالمنام؟
In a dream?
بالمنام، قال شربوني مية الحياة.
In a dream, she says they made me drink the water of life.
قال يا ابني ما حدا عاش بهالعمر هذا، بعمري.
She says, my son, no one has lived to this age, to my age.
محمد بيصير ابن ضرتك؟ محمد، محمد أبو شيخو؟
Is Muhammad the son of your co-wife? Muhammad, Muhammad Abu
Sheikho?
محمد، محمد ابن ضرتي، ما بي حدا غير الله...
Muhammad, Muhammad is the son of my co-wife, there is no one
but God...
خلف الله عليك وعليه، جابني... شو أسوي؟
May God reward you and him, he brought me... what can I do?
حدي وتي أهل الخير إنتوا، وأنا عايش ويه ولاد... وبيّ الله.
You are good people around me, and I am living with the
children... and God is with me.
هلق أنتِ ما إجاكي ولاد؟
So you didn't have any children?
لا.
No.
ما إجاكي ولاد؟
You didn't have children?
لا ما... جبت ثلاث ضراير علي...
No, I didn't... I brought three co-wives upon myself...
اثنين حشاك ماتن، ظلت بنت درمش عاد الله انطانا حمودة...
Two of them, saving your presence, died, the daughter of
Darmash remained, and God gave us Hammouda...
أهلي يعني أمي، العزيزية، من العزيزية أمي ضرتها.
My family, I mean my mother, Al-Aziziyah, my mother is from
Al-Aziziyah, her co-wife.
الله يخلي ولادكم، الله يخلي حريماتكم...
May God protect your children, may God protect your wives...
شلون ومحمد معك؟ شلونه؟
How is Muhammad treating you? How is he?
خلف الله عليه، يجيب لي الأكل والشارب ويا ولاد...
May God reward him, he brings me food and drink and the
children...
وشنو شفتي حدي وتي أهل الخير... حديني وأنا عايش ويه ولد وبيّ
الله...
And as you can see, the good people are around me... around
me, and I am living with the boy, and God is with me...
شو عم تقول يا أمي؟ يا حجة دلة؟
What are you saying mother? Hajja Dalla?
ما بيها، الموتة التمام يا ابني ما جات التمام، إيش أسوي...
There's nothing to it, the complete death, my son, the
complete death hasn't come, what can I do...
العمر كله إن شاء الله، طولي بالك.
May you live a long life God willing, be patient.
شقد صار له الحجي ميت؟ الحجي، الحجي...
How long has the Hajji been dead? The Hajji, the Hajji...
يقول أبوي الله يرحمه شقد صار له ميت؟
He says, my father, may God have mercy on him, how long has
he been dead?
إي والله ما أعرف صار يجي 50، 60 سنة.
Yes by God, I don't know, it's been maybe 50, 60 years.
يقول من زمان يعني، وبجوز هي ما بتعرف... يعني تقريباً بالـ 25
سنة أبوي صار له متوفي.
She means a long time ago, and maybe she doesn't know... I
mean, it's been about 25 years since my father passed away.
قديش كان عمره؟
How old was he?
والله بالـ 95.
By God, around 95.
ما شاء الله، العمر كله...
Mashallah, a full life...
كان الأسد طيب...
Assad was alive...
قال لسا كان الأسد طيب من توفى الحجي...
She says Assad was still alive when the Hajji died...
الأسد، الأسد حافظ؟
Assad, Hafez al-Assad?
إيوه، حافظ.
Yes, Hafez.
بتعرفي لحافظ الأسد؟
Do you know Hafez al-Assad?
يقول بتعرفينه لحافظ الأسد؟ الأسد بتعرفينه؟
He says, do you know Hafez al-Assad? Do you know Assad?
إي...
Yes...
إي إي.
Yes, yes.
يقول بتعرفينه لحافظ الأسد؟
He says, do you know Hafez al-Assad?
ما أدري إيش هو...
I don't know what it is...
يقول هي سمعانة إنه كان في أسد... إيوه.
He says she has heard that there was an Assad... yes.
شلون اليوم تقضي يومك؟ يعني الحجة كيف بتقضي يومها؟ إيش
بتساوي؟
How do you spend your day today? I mean, how does the Hajja
spend her day? What does she do?
والله بصلاتها وبعبادة...
By God, with her prayers and worship...
كيف؟
How?
بتصلي، بتصوم، إيمت ما تبرك، تشوفها باركة عم تسبح وبتصيح يا
الله، يا رب،
She prays, she fasts, whenever she sits down, you see her
sitting praising God and crying out Oh God, Oh Lord,
بتصيح لربها، هي أكتر شي... وبالصلاة، مقضيتها أكتر شي عالصلاة
والعبادة.
she cries out to her Lord, this is mostly it... and in
prayer, she spends most of her time on prayer and worship.
بتمشي؟
Does she walk?
إي بتمشي.
Yes, she walks.
الفرنسي، عوين الفرنسي، شفناهم...
The French, the eyes of the French, we saw them...
تتذكري لفرنساوي يا حجة؟
Do you remember the French, Hajja?
يقول تتذكرين الفرنسي؟
He says, do you remember the French?
إي الفرنساوي شفته، الإنكليز شفته... هذولا كلهم شفتهم...
Yes, I saw the French, I saw the English... I saw all of
these...
يقول هذول كلياتهم شفتهم...
She says I saw all of these...
الفرنسي، ما بي مصاري، بس ليرات ومجيديات.
The French, there was no money, only Liras and Majidiyyas.
مجيديات وليرات، يقول أول ما كان في عملة.
Majidiyyas and Liras, she says at first there was no
currency.
الأتراك والعثمانيين بتتذكريهم؟
Do you remember the Turks and the Ottomans?
نعم.
Yes.
يقول أتراك والعصملية بتتذكرينهم؟ إنتِ تتذكرين أتراك
والعصملي؟ على دور العصملي؟
He says do you remember the Turks and the Ottomans? Do you
remember the Turks and the Ottomans? During the Ottoman era?
أتذكر...
I remember...
يقول أتذكر، أتذكر هالحكي، إيوه...
She says I remember, I remember this talk, yes...
ما شاء الله.
Mashallah.
مرأة كبيرة...
An old woman...
الدنيا كانت أولي أحلى ولا هلق؟
Was the world better in the past or now?
يقول الدنيا أولي أحسن جانت ولا هالحز؟
He says, was the world better in the past or right now?
والله أولي، هالحز الدنيا ضاعت.
By God, in the past, right now the world is lost.
يقول الدنيا ضاعت قامت تجذب.
She says the world is lost, it started to lie.
بتقولي يابا شقد عدى عليي شيء، بتهيألك ما عدى على حدا؟
You say, oh man, so much has passed over me, do you think no
one has gone through what you have?
شيء ما فات...
Things didn't pass...
كنتي تروحي على كلس؟
Did you use to go to Kilis?
نعم.
Yes.
كنتي تروحي على كلس إنتِ؟
Did you use to go to Kilis?
يقول جنتي تروحين على كلس أولي؟
He says, did you use to go to Kilis in the past?
إي، ع كلس جنا نروح، ما بي عسكر، ننطيهم فرنكين ونروح على كلس
Yes, we used to go to Kilis, there were no soldiers, we
would give them two francs and go to Kilis,
نتقرض ونجي... ما يقارشونا بشي...
we'd borrow and come back... they wouldn't bother us with
anything...
نتغرض ونجي يقول، أولي كان بلدهم كلس يعني ما كانوا يروحوا
على...
We'd borrow and come back she says, in the past their city
was Kilis, meaning they wouldn't go to...
وعلى جبل النمرود رحنا ع تركيا... رحنا على تركيا...
And to Mount Nemrut we went to Turkey... we went to
Turkey...
قال أنا ثلاث مرات أروح على حلب، أعد ضد...
He said I went to Aleppo three times, I count against...
جانا تيمار قال تروحون تريدون ديار بكر؟
Timar came to us and said, "Do you want to go to
Diyarbakir?"
كان أبعثكم هناك.
"I could send you there."
قالوا شبابنا إحنا نريد بلادنا، إي قال كيفكم على كيفكم.
Our youth said, "We want our country." He said, "Yes, as you
wish, as you wish."
قال بدكم بلادكم عسوريا بترجعوا عسوريا،
He said, "You want your country, you return to Syria."
واللي بده يتم بتركيا يتم بتركيا.
"And whoever wants to stay in Turkey, stays in Turkey."
قال لا والله بدنا نروح عسوريا.
He said, "No, by God, we want to go to Syria."
بدي.. يعني هلق أنتو الحجة نشوفك كيف تمشي.
I want... I mean now, you Hajja, let's see how you walk.
صلي.
Pray.
أستاذي يقول بدنا نشوفك شلون بدك تصلين، شلون عشان تقومين
تمشين.
My teacher says we want to see how you pray, how you stand
up and walk.
بالعمر ها عشان تقومين تمشين.
At this age, so you can stand up and walk.
أنا من رجلي وين ما أقوم ألا أقومك.
With my legs, I cannot stand unless I force myself.
إي قومي امشي قدامه.
Yes, stand up and walk in front of him.
يا رب.
Oh Lord.
تعذب لا تعذبك.
It tortures, don't let it torture you.
يا رب يا بسم الله الرحمن الرحيم.
Oh Lord, oh in the name of God, the Most Gracious, the Most
Merciful.
يا الله.
Oh God.
ما شاء الله.
Mashallah.
وين بتروح؟
Where does she go?
والله أكتر شي الله يعزك بتروح على بيت المي،
By God, mostly, may God honor you, she goes to the bathroom,
ومرات وقت الزيتون...
And sometimes during olive season...
أدن العصر أكون هلق بدي أصلي.
The afternoon call to prayer happened, I want to pray now.
أدن للعصر ها بدك تصلين، يلا دي هلق صار وقت الصلاة، سبحان
الله.
The afternoon call to prayer happened, ah you want to pray.
Come on, go ahead, now it's prayer time, Subhanallah.
ارتاحي يا أمي ارتاحي.
Rest, my mother, rest.
يقول ارتاحي.
He says rest.
يلا بدي أسجد هلق للصلاة.
Come on, I want to prostrate now for prayer.
تعالي لهون، تعالي تعالي تعالي.
Come here, come, come, come.
يا الله.
Oh God.
ما شاء الله بتصلي، بتصوم شهر رمضان كله بتصوم؟
Mashallah. Does she pray, does she fast? She fasts the whole
month of Ramadan?
أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome.
أهلاً وسهلين بالشباب.
Double welcome to the youth.
مين بتصيري للحجة؟
How are you related to the Hajja?
بنت عمي اللزم.
My first cousin.
أهلاً وسهلاً، الحجة ربيتك الحجة دلي؟
Welcome. Did the Hajja raise you, Hajja Delli?
ماني وعيت لسا عمري ست أشهر وهي ربتني.
I didn't even gain consciousness, I was only six months old
and she raised me.
ما شاء الله، شقد عمرك أنتي؟
Mashallah, how old are you?
خمسة وسبعين.
Seventy-five.
خمسة وسبعين، ما شاء الله، ما شاء الله، الله يطول بعمرك.
Seventy-five. Mashallah, Mashallah. May God prolong your
life.
أبو شيخو أنا عم شم ريحة، ريحة خبز.
Abu Sheikho, I'm smelling a scent, the smell of bread.
إي والله عم نخبز يا أستاذ مصطفى.
Yes by God, we are baking, Mr. Mustafa.
خلينا نشوف الحجة عم بتصلي هلق.
Let's see the Hajja is praying now.
تفضل.
Go ahead.
تفضل تفضل حاج.
Go ahead, go ahead, Haj.
مين عم يخبز أم شيخو؟
Who is baking, Umm Sheikho?
والله أم شيخو عم تخبز.
By God, Umm Sheikho is baking.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام.
And upon you be peace.
الله يعطيكِ العافية. شلونك يا أم شيخو؟
May God give you health. How are you, Umm Sheikho?
الحمد لله، إنت شلونك أستاذ.
Praise be to God. How are you, teacher?
الحمد لله، خلوني أبرك شوي هيك جنبكم.
Praise be to God. Let me sit a bit next to you.
تعا تعا، هذا وراي هذا، ع شاشة البطون تبعك؟ ابنك؟
Come, come, this one behind me, is he from your own flesh
and blood? Your son?
إي ع شاشة البطون هذا.
Yes, he is from my own flesh and blood.
شو اسمه الله يخليه؟
What's his name, may God keep him?
خليل اسمه.
His name is Khalil.
يا أهلاً وسهلاً، والصبية مين؟
Welcome. And who is the young lady?
الصبية بتصير بنت قريبتنا.
The young lady is the daughter of our relative.
يا أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome.
شو عم تساوي أنتي؟
What are you making?
والله خبزنا وسوينا محمرة وسوينا دوبركي.
By God, we baked, and we made Muhammara, and we made
Dûberkî.
شو هاد؟ هاد هو الخبز الأبيض؟
What is this? Is this the white bread?
هذا الخبز الأبيض يا أستاذ.
This is the white bread, teacher.
هذا شو بتسموه أنتو؟
What do you call this?
هذا طحين زيرو عم نخبزه نحنا.
This is zero grade flour, we are baking it.
هون، شو مساوية هون؟
Here, what are you making here?
هون يا أستاذ، هذا محمرة.
Here, teacher, this is Muhammara.
وهون كأنه في زعتر، في دوبركي.
And here it looks like there's thyme, there's Dûberkî.
لا هون في دوبركي على بصل.
No, here there is Dûberkî with onion.
على بصل؟ شو بتسموها أنتو هي الدوبركي على بصل؟
With onion? What do you call this Dûberkî with onion?
هذا نحنا بنسويه أكلة شتوية بناكلها بالشتا.
This, we make it as a winter dish, we eat it in the winter.
وهدول شو عم تساوي هدول؟
And these, what are you making these?
هذول كمان محمرة.
These are also Muhammara.
المحمرة عندكم هون هيك تراث يعني تقريباً؟
Is Muhammara a heritage here for you, pretty much?
إي بناكلها نحنا بنحبها بالشتا أكتر شي نساويها.
Yes, we eat it, we love it. We mostly make it in the winter.
إي شو هي التبلة هلق؟
Yes, what is the filling now?
التبلة دبس فليفلة وقلينا بصل معه، وهي هي والله يا أستاذ.
The filling is pepper paste, and we fried onions with it,
and that's it by God, teacher.
فقط دبس فليفلة وبصل؟ حبة سودة...؟
Only pepper paste and onion? Black seed...?
لا، بس دبس فليفلة وبصل، ما حطينا له.
No, just pepper paste and onion. We didn't add that to it.
هيدا شو اسمه هيدا؟
This, what is this called?
هذا دفت الخبز.
This is the bread board.
وهون الشوبك تبعك؟
And here is your rolling pin?
الشوبك تبعي هذا هو.
My rolling pin is this one.
أيوا ما شفناه يلا.
Ah, we didn't see it, go ahead.
كله عم تخبزوا؟
Are you baking all of it?
والله يا أستاذ قبل ما يجينا الخبز...
By God, teacher, before bread came to us...
الله يساعد الحرمة يا أستاذ.
May God help the woman, teacher.
كنا نهار إي نهار لا كنا نخبز.
We used to bake one day yes, one day no.
كل تلت أيام كنا نخبز، كنا نروح ع اعزاز نجيب أكياس طحين أم
الخمسين كيلو.
Every three days we used to bake. We used to go to Azaz to
get 50kg bags of flour.
والخبز كان غالي، ونحنا عيلة يعني ولاد أختي كمان إجو من عفرين
لعندي.
And bread was expensive. And we are a family, I mean my
sister's kids also came from Afrin to my place.
صرنا عيلة كبيرة يعني، من تمن أشخاص صرنا إدعش.
We became a big family, like, from 8 people we became 11.
صرنا نخبز، ما نلحق ع الخبز صرنا نخبز.
We started baking. We couldn't keep up with the bread, so we
started baking.
هلق صار يجيكم خبز من برا.
Now bread comes to you from outside.
إي عم يجينا خبز الله يعطيهم العافية، خبز المعونة عم يجينا
شوي توفر علينا.
Yes, bread comes to us, may God give them health. The aid
bread comes to us, it saved us a bit.
يعطيهم ألف عافية والله يحميهم يا رب.
May God give them a thousand healths, and may God protect
them, oh Lord.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
ريحتها كتير طيبة.
It smells very good.
هلق أبو شيخو بيساعدك دائماً ولا بس قدامنا هلق عالتلفزيون عم
يساوي حاله بيساعد؟
Now, does Abu Sheikho always help you, or is he just
pretending to help now in front of us on television?
هلق دوم بيساعدني أبو شيخو.
Now, Abu Sheikho always helps me.
أنا أكلات تقيلة بساعدها لأم شيخو.
I help Umm Sheikho with the heavy meals.
بيساعدني بيساعدني والله أبو شيخو ما بعيفني لحالي، ما بسخى
علي.
He helps me, he helps me, by God, Abu Sheikho. He doesn't
leave me alone, he can't bear to see me work alone.
يعني أبو شيخو منيح معك.
So Abu Sheikho is good to you.
لا منيح.
Indeed, he's good.
بركي هلق بيشوفوه عالتلفزيون بيكافئوه على أنه منيح معك.
Maybe now they will see him on television and reward him
because he's good to you.
إي منيح معي لا حرام يعطيه العافية.
Yes, he's good to me, it's a sin to say otherwise, may God
give him health.
النار ما هي عالية هيك كتير؟
Isn't the fire too high like this?
لا أبو شيخو...
No, Abu Sheikho...
تمام عشان ما تطلع عجين.
Perfect, so it doesn't turn out doughy.
يا ستي الله يعطيكِ العافية.
My lady, may God give you health.
يعافيك.
May He give you health.
سلم إيديكي.
Bless your hands.
أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome.
من ريحته يعني طيب، صحتين وهنا.
From its smell, I mean, it's good. Bon appetit.
أهلاً وسهلاً نورتوا ضيعتنا.
Welcome, you lit up our village.
تسلم يا خيو تسلم.
Thank you brother, thank you.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام.
And upon you be peace.
هلق تركناكم جوا عم تخبزي يا أم شيخو.
Now we left you inside baking, Umm Sheikho.
أنتي وحماتك هلق بركتين تحت شجرة التوت بساحة الضيعة.
You and your mother-in-law are now sitting under the
mulberry tree in the village square.
خلونا نبرك معكم شوي.
Let us sit with you a bit.
شلونك يا خالتي؟
How are you, my aunt?
أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome.
تعرفي على حالك، اسمك شو اسمك؟
Introduce yourself. Your name, what is your name?
مريم.
Meryem.
أهلاً وسهلاً بالحجة مريم، الحجة؟
Welcome Hajja Meryem. And the Hajja?
أم منان.
Umm Mannan.
أهلاً وسهلاً، شفناكِ جوا.
Welcome. We saw you inside.
هلق شو عم تساووا هون أنتو؟
Now, what are you doing here?
نشتغل فلاحين.
We work as farmers.
فلاحين أبوي والله.
Farmers, my son, by God.
هالإيام إيش في عندكم شغل بالأرض؟
These days, what work do you have in the land?
عندنا الحز أول كان في حصاد، في رجاد، في دراس.
Before, we had harvesting, stacking, threshing.
الحز ما في شغل، باركين وقاعدين.
Right now there is no work. We are sitting and resting.
والحجة مريم شو عم تساوي؟
And what is Hajja Meryem doing?
والله ما أساوي كل شي، لا شغلة ولا عملة، قاعدين.
By God, I don't do anything. No job, no work. We are
sitting.
وين ولادك؟
Where are your children?
ولادي بتركيا.
My children are in Turkey.
بتركيا؟ شقد عندك ولاد؟
In Turkey? How many children do you have?
متجوزين قلتلك، تلات بنات وتلات صبيان.
They are married, I told you. Three girls and three boys.
الله يخليلك ياهم.
May God keep them for you.
هلق حدا قال لي قبل ما آجي لهون.
Now, someone told me before I came here.
همس بإذني وقال لي الحجة مريم بتعرف تغني كويس، وصوتها حلو.
Whispered in my ear and told me Hajja Meryem knows how to
sing well, and her voice is beautiful.
وبتغني أغاني الضيعة هون.
And she sings the village's songs here.
فأنتي وأم منان وأم شيخو والحجة رح تغنوا لنا هلق هيك شي.
So you, and Umm Mannan, and Umm Sheikho, and the Hajja will
sing for us now something like...
شي من من يعني من تراث الضيعة، فلكلور الضيعة، غنى الضيعة.
Something from the heritage of the village, the folklore of
the village, the singing of the village.
إيش بدك تغني؟
What do you want to sing?
إيش بدك أغني لك؟
What do you want me to sing for you?
تغني تركي بتعرفي، تركي أحسن يعني.
You sing Turkish, you know, Turkish is better, I mean.
طيب غني تركي يلا.
Okay, sing Turkish, go ahead.
أنتي بتغني هن بيردوا وراكي؟
Do you sing and they repeat after you?
لا هية بحدها تغني أحسن.
No, she sings on her own, it's better.
يا رب دخيلك.
Oh Lord, have mercy.
Ya kî bimçe... wey te doyê ma tar dibe...
[Preparing her voice / Speaking local dialect]
عيني أوريد...
My eyes want...
لا لا.
No, no.
صوته عم بيقول...
His voice is saying...
لا لا الصوت ما بروح.
No, no, the voice won't go away.
تفضلي.
Go ahead.
Şu dağın ardında bir taş olaydım.
If I were a stone behind that mountain.
Gelene gidene yoldaş olaydım.
If I were a companion to the comer and goer.
Şu dağın ardında bir taş olaydım.
If I were a stone behind that mountain.
Gelene gidene yoldaş olaydım.
If I were a companion to the comer and goer.
Köprüden geçtim, köprü kırıldı.
I passed the bridge, the bridge broke.
Köprüden indim, köprü yıkıldı.
I went down from the bridge, the bridge collapsed.
Anasız babasız boynum büküldü.
Without mother, without father, my neck was bent.
Ben bir öksüzdüm, ortada kaldım.
I was an orphan, I was left in the middle.
ما شاء الله! بدي زقفة.
Mashallah! I want a clap.
إيش كنتي عم تقولي بالعربي؟ شو كانت عم تقول يعني ترجمي لي
إياها.
What were you saying in Arabic? What was she saying?
Translate it for me.
يقول ورا هالجبل حجرة.
It says, behind this mountain is a stone.
والرايح وجاية أصير له وديع.
And the one coming and going, I become a companion to him.
ويعني يتيمة وأنا عشت بغير حدا.
Meaning an orphan, and I lived with no one.
يتيمة.
An orphan.
عم تغني عن حالها؟
Is she singing about herself?
إي هلق...
Yes now...
بتحكي تركي، وبتحكي عربي وإيش بتحكي كمان؟
You speak Turkish, and you speak Arabic, and what else do
you speak?
وكردي وعربي وتركي.
Kurdish, Arabic, and Turkish.
كلياتكم هيك بتحكوا؟
Do all of you speak like this?
إي كلهم يعرفوا.
Yes, they all know.
في شي أغنية تانية بالعربي أو بالكردي؟
Is there another song in Arabic or in Kurdish?
بالتركي تقولي لها دولانا قول دولانا...
In Turkish you tell her Dolana, say Dolana...
طيب طيب بالسعودي؟
Okay, okay, what about in Saudi?
إيه ساعدها.
Yeah, help her out.
إي يلا اسمعي، لا، وحدة تانية، خالتي...
Yeah come on listen, no, another one, auntie...
وحدة تانية، والله مابعرفها، كان غنيتها بس مابعرفها.
Another one, I swear I don't know it, otherwise I would have
sung it, but I don't know it.
تفضلي، تفضلي، دولانا.
Go ahead, go ahead, Dolana.
يا حرام، إياك ما تدوي بس.
Oh my, just make sure you don't mess up.
صوتك حلو يا خالتي والله.
Your voice is beautiful, auntie, really.
عم بيقول صوتك حلو يا خالتي.
He's saying your voice is beautiful, auntie.
إي حلو حلو.
Yeah, beautiful, beautiful.
تفضلي.
Go ahead.
يلا.
Let's go.
بس إياك بس...
Just make sure...
بيده يا كيبه... دولانا رندل إي... والله لا نعرفها، ماني
حافظة...
Bêde ya kî be... dolana rindê lê... I swear we don't know
it, I haven't memorized it...
Dolana yar dolana.
Wander around, my love, wander around.
Dolana gin dolana.
Wander around, until the day wanders.
Dolana yar dolana.
Wander around, my love, wander around.
Dolana gin dolana.
Wander around, until the day wanders.
Bağa endim nar için.
I went down to the vineyard for pomegranates.
Gül devşirdim yar için.
I gathered roses for my love.
Bunca memleket gezdim.
I wandered around so many places.
Karagözlü yar için.
For my black-eyed love.
Bağa endim üzüme.
I went down to the vineyard for grapes.
Çubuk değdi gözüme.
A twig hit my eye.
Çubuk seni keserim.
Twig, I will cut you.
Yar göründü gözüme.
My love appeared to my eye.
Dolana yar dolana.
Wander around, my love, wander around.
Dolana hoş dolana.
Wander around pleasantly.
Bağa endim nar için.
I went down to the vineyard for pomegranates.
Gül devşirdim yar için.
I gathered roses for my love.
Bunca memleket gezdim.
I wandered around so many places.
Karagözlü yar için.
For my black-eyed love.
Bağa endim üzüme.
I went down to the vineyard for grapes.
Çubuk değdi gözüme.
A twig hit my eye.
Çubuk seni keserim.
Twig, I will cut you.
Yar göründü gözüme.
My love appeared to my eye.
الله يعطيك العافية. شو قالت، ترجميلي؟
God give you health. What did she say, translate for me?
بتقول رحت ع الكرم، نزلت ع الكرم.
She says I went to the vineyard, I went down to the
vineyard.
قطفت العنب وتشوبق د... صاب عيني.
I picked grapes and the twig... hit my eye.
ع الرمان... ع الرمان.
For pomegranates... for pomegranates.
ع الرمان... حشيت الرمان ها.
For pomegranates... I picked pomegranates, right.
عفواً.
Excuse me.
حشيت ال... يا bağa endim nar için, gül devşirdim yar için.
I picked the... oh, I went down to the vineyard for
pomegranates, I gathered roses for my love.
Bunca memleket gezdim karagözlü yar için... على قد ما دورت
من شان العيون السود.
I wandered around so many places for my black-eyed love...
As much as I searched, it was for the black eyes.
العيون السود.
The black eyes.
أيوا... يا bağa endim üzüme, çubuk değdi gözüme.
Yes... oh, I went down to the vineyard for grapes, a twig
hit my eye.
Çubuk seni keserim, yar göründü gözüme.
Twig, I will cut you, my love appeared to my eye.
الله يعطيكم العافية. شكراً إلكم، انبسطنا معكم كتير.
God give you health. Thank you, we enjoyed our time with you
a lot.
الجو شوب، بس تحت شجرة التوت الأحمر برود.
The weather is hot, but under the red mulberry tree it's
cool.
ده برود إي...
Yeah it's cool, yeah...
إي والله برد.
Yes, by God, it's cool.
مرساوا قرية حدودية، محاذية للشريط الحدودي مع تركيا بالضبط.
Mersawa is a border village, exactly adjacent to the border
strip with Turkey.
وهي تقع بين قلعتي النبي هوري جنوباً، وراوندا شمالاً.
And it is located between the castles of Nebi Houri to the
south, and Rawanda to the north.
البعض قال بأنه قصة تسمية مرساوا، لأنه هي في الوسط ما بين
قلعتي النبي هوري وراوندا.
Some said that the story behind naming Mersawa is because it
is in the middle between the castles of Nebi Houri and
Rawanda.
لنعرف قصة هالضيعة الحقيقية والتاريخ الحقيقي، رح يكون معنا
العم محمد عابد العجار، أبو اسماعيل.
To know the true story and real history of this village,
Uncle Muhammad Abid Al-Ajjar, Abu Ismail, will be with us.
من أهالي الضيعة، ومهتم بالضيعة، ليحكيلنا عن تاريخها.
From the people of the village, and someone interested in
the village, to tell us about its history.
يعطيك العافية عمي أبو اسماعيل.
God give you health, Uncle Abu Ismail.
الله يعافيك، أهلاً وسهلاً.
God give you health, welcome.
الله يخليك. احكيلي قصة هالضيعة، شقد عمرها؟
May God protect you. Tell me the story of this village, how
old is it?
والله من ميتين سنة تقريباً.
Well, it's about two hundred years old.
نحنا منسمع من ميتين سنة هالضيعة تأسست.
We hear that this village was founded two hundred years ago.
ويجوز هي أكتر من هيك، بس نحنا نوعى من تقريباً ميتين سنة
منعلم إنه هالضيعة موجودة.
And it might be older than that, but we have been aware for
about two hundred years that this village exists.
شلون تأسست يعني؟ من وين كانوا أهلها؟
How was it founded? Where were its people from?
أهلها نازحين، اجوا من برا.
Its people were displaced, they came from outside.
من وين؟
From where?
من دير صوان.
From Deyr Siwan.
أهالي سكان منبج، نحنا كنا من حماة أصلنا.
Residents of Manbij, we were originally from Hama.
من حماة رحتوا على منبج، وبعدين على دير صوان؟
From Hama you went to Manbij, and then to Deyr Siwan?
إي، جينا على دير صوان.
Yes, we came to Deyr Siwan.
وجدنا عنده معز، جاب المعز لهون.
And our grandfather had goats, he brought the goats here.
شتّى هون، ربيع كويس.
He spent the winter here, the spring was good.
وشاف هالأرض، وشاف أهالي سكان الضيعة القديمين الأولين، اشترى
منهم أراضي، واستملك.
And he saw this land, and saw the original ancient
inhabitants of the village, he bought lands from them, and
took ownership.
واجوا قرايبينه معه، وقعدوا وسكنوا بهالضيعة، وكبرت الضيعة
من...
And his relatives came with him, and they sat and lived in
this village, and the village grew from...
لما بتقول نحنا، مين إنتو؟
When you say we, who are you?
نحنا العرب اللي جينا.
We are the Arabs who came.
عشاير يعني؟ أي عشيرة؟
Tribes, you mean? Which tribe?
عشيرة بوبنا.
The Bubanna tribe.
وفي غيركم؟
And are there others besides you?
في عنا مجادمة، بعد منا اجوا كمان.
We have the Majadima, they also came after us.
إنتو البوبنا، جيتوا من حماة على منبج، على دير صوان لهون؟
You the Bubanna, came from Hama to Manbij, to Deyr Siwan, to
here?
إي، على حكي جدنا.
Yes, according to our grandfather's talk.
من كم سنة؟
How many years ago?
من ميتين سنة هاي الشغلة.
This happened two hundred years ago.
طيب، والأكراد مين فيهون؟
Okay, and who is there among the Kurds?
الأكراد في بيت حسو رشكو، اجوا من زعرى.
The Kurds, there's the Heso Reshko family, they came from
Za're.
وفي بيت أحمد رشو، اجوا من حسن ديرلي.
And there's the Ahmed Resho family, they came from Hasan
Derli.
وفي بيت حمو يوسف، اجوا من قره تبه.
And there's the Hemo Yusiv family, they came from Qeretepe.
وفي بيت رشيد خرخز بيقولولن.
And there's the Reshid Khirkhiz family, they call them.
اجوا من دير صوان كمان هدول.
These also came from Deyr Siwan.
كمان رعاة معز؟
Also goat herders?
إي هلق صاروا أملاك، هدول كان أولي معز كلهن إي.
Yes, now they have properties, but formerly they were all
goat herders, yes.
وكنتوا كلياتكم معازة؟
And were you all goat herders?
كلنا معازة كنا.
We were all goat herders.
السبب ليش معازة؟ ليش مو غنم مثلاً؟
What's the reason for being goat herders? Why not sheep, for
example?
إي هون منطقة حرشية، مشان ما بيعطوا علف...
Well, this is a forested area, so they don't have to give
fodder...
المعز بيقاوم أكتر.
Goats are more resilient.
طيب هون في مي؟ كان في مي هون قديماً؟
Okay, is there water here? Was there water here in the past?
في نهر، نهر صابون صوي اسمه.
There is a river, called the Sabun Suyu river.
نهر الصافي نحنا نقول له بالعربي، نهر الصافي هذا.
We call it the Safi river in Arabic, this is the Safi river.
بالصيف بينشف، بيقطعوه من فوق.
In the summer it dries up, they cut it off from upstream.
إي وبالشتي موجود، للشهر السادس تقريباً بيضل عنا هالنهر جاري.
Yes, and in the winter it is present, until about the sixth
month this river keeps flowing here.
يعني معناها إنتو جيتوا لهون على أطراف النهر والأحراش.
So that means you came here to the banks of the river and
the forests.
أيوة، أيوة بالضبط.
Yes, yes exactly.
طيب، خليني ارجع لمرساوا. من وين اجا اسم مرساوا؟
Alright, let me go back to Mersawa. Where did the name
Mersawa come from?
مرساوا... قلعة النبي هوري، هي قلعة سيروس جنوبنا.
Mersawa... the Nebi Houri castle, which is the Cyrrhus
castle to our south.
وقلعة راوندا شمالها، صايرة بالأراضي التركية.
And the Rawanda castle is to its north, located in the
Turkish territories.
أولي ما كان في حدود، ما في شغلات هيك.
Formerly there were no borders, no such things.
كان في نقطة هون اسمها المنتصف، يعني مرساوا.
There was a point here called the middle, meaning Mersawa.
المنتصف؟
The middle?
المنتصف، تقريباً يعني هيك بمنتصف...
The middle, almost like right in the middle...
وناس عم بيقولوا، مروا اتنين سوا، سألوا عليهم قالوا مروا سوا.
And some people say, two passed together, they asked about
them, they said they "passed together" (marru sawa).
على أساس هاي، هيك تأسست مرساوا، بهذا الشكل هذا.
Based on this, this is how Mersawa was founded, in this
manner.
هذا وادي؟ شو هاد الوادي؟
This is a valley? What is this valley?
لا مو وادي، الوادي تحت، هداك الوادي.
No, not a valley, the valley is below, that one is the
valley.
هذا بيمر هالواد بالشتي بيجي منه مي، لأنه صاير بوسط.
This valley, in winter water flows through it, because it is
in the middle.
المي من هون ومن هون تقلب عليه، بيجي بيروح ع النهر، ع نهر
صابون صوي.
Water from here and here pours into it, it comes and goes to
the river, to the Sabun Suyu river.
يعني واضح إنه القرية مبنية على هضبة.
So it is clear that the village is built on a plateau.
إي على هضبة هون، إي.
Yes, on a plateau here, yes.
هلق المنطقة عمي أبو اسماعيل، المنطقة فيها آثار؟
Now, the area Uncle Abu Ismail, does the area have ruins?
حوالين مرساوا في آثار؟
Are there ruins around Mersawa?
آثار روماني، روماني.
Roman ruins, Roman.
في القرية هون روماني؟
In the village here it's Roman?
في شي آثار ما زالت موجودة؟
Are there any ruins still existing?
لا ما في، شغلات بسيطة كتير، يعني مبين إنه آثار روماني
بهالضيعة هاي.
No there aren't, very simple things, meaning it's clear
there are Roman ruins in this village.
سمعت عن الكرسانة، شو الكرسانة؟
I heard about the Karsana, what is the Karsana?
الكرسانة... فيها معبر بين طريق قلعة النبي هوري وقلعة راوندا.
The Karsana... has a crossing between the road of Nebi Houri
castle and Rawanda castle.
في هنيك متل حلة المي، جرن مي بيسقوا فيه الدواب.
There is something like a water basin there, a water trough
where they water the animals.
أو هو زيارة، أو هو ما بنعرف معبد، أو هو شو، لأنه موجود حتى
الآن.
Or it is a shrine, or we don't know if it's a temple, or
what it is, because it exists until now.
هاي الكرسانة، يعني مكان بيزوروه الناس ويتبركوا فيه.
This is the Karsana, meaning a place people visit and seek
blessings in.
القديمين يتبركوا، هلق جيل هلق بتعرف إنت...
The ancients used to seek blessings, now the current
generation, you know...
طيب، شو بيحكوا أهل الضيعة؟
Okay, what do the people of the village speak?
بيحكوا بالكردي وبالعربي.
They speak Kurdish and Arabic.
الاتنين سوا؟
Both together?
وبتركي كمان.
And Turkish as well.
كل أهل القرية؟
All the people of the village?
كل أهل القرية ما شاء الله اغلبيتها.
All the people of the village, Mashallah, the majority of
it.
الصغار اللي عمرهم هلق بالعشرين خمسة وعشرين بيحكوا كردي
وعربي.
The young ones who are now twenty or twenty-five speak
Kurdish and Arabic.
ولكن تركي ما بيعرفوا، لا.
But Turkish they don't know, no.
هلق صارت اللهجة التركية ماشية، وصاروا يتعلموا.
Now the Turkish dialect is becoming common, and they are
learning.
واللي راحوا يشتغلوا برا واجوا، صار معهم اللهجة التركية.
And those who went to work outside and came back, they
picked up the Turkish dialect.
الله يعطيك العافية عمي أبو اسماعيل. شكراً إلك.
God give you health, Uncle Abu Ismail. Thank you.
على راسي، أهلي وسهلي.
On my head, welcome.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله وبركاته.
And upon you be peace, and the mercy of God and His
blessings.
يعطيك العافية.
God give you health.
الله يعافيك، أهلاً وسهلاً أستاذ، أهلاً وسهلاً.
God give you health, welcome sir, welcome.
نتعرف عليك؟
May we know you?
اسمي شريف أبو محمد.
My name is Sherif Abu Muhammad.
أهلاً وسهلاً فيكم عمي أبو محمد.
Welcome to you, Uncle Abu Muhammad.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
خلينا نمشي، عم نتمشى...
Let's walk, we are taking a stroll...
احكولي عن طبيعة هالضيعة؟ شو طبيعتها؟ شلون وضعها؟
Tell me about the nature of this village? What is its
nature? How is its situation?
والله الحمدلله، الوضع منيح.
Well thank God, the situation is good.
يعني ضيعة ريفية، يعني فيها الفلاحة المشهورة بالزيتون الكروم.
I mean it's a rural village, it has farming that is famous
for olives, vineyards.
ويعني بيزرعوا حبوب، بقوليات.
And they plant grains, legumes.
يعني أمور الفلاحة.
Meaning farming matters.
يعني طبيعة الناس هون زراعيين؟
So the nature of the people here is agricultural?
زراعيين.
Agricultural.
بيربوا أغنام؟
Do they raise sheep?
إي بيربوا أغنام.
Yes, they raise sheep.
بيربوا ماعز؟
Do they raise goats?
ماعز كمان.
Goats too.
أكتر ماعز ولا أغنام؟
More goats or sheep?
لا أغنام أكتر.
No, sheep are more.
الناس هون سهلين صعبين، شو طبيعتهم؟
Are the people here easygoing or difficult, what is their
nature?
والله يعني بسطاء. شعب هون عنا بالضيعة شعب بسيط.
Well, they are simple. The people here in our village are
simple people.
يعني بيحب الضيف، كريمين، ومتواضعين.
I mean they love guests, they are generous, and humble.
متواضعين بشكل، شايف كيف.
Incredibly humble, you see.
خاصة بتعرف الفلاح بيضل متواضع.
Especially, you know, a farmer remains humble.
وأمورهم الحمدلله ماشي الحال، في بعض الصعوبات، الحمدلله.
And their affairs, thank God, are okay. There are some
difficulties, thank God.
عندكم مدرسة هون؟
Do you have a school here?
إي عنا مدرسة.
Yes, we have a school.
شقد صار لها؟
How long has it been there?
والله صار لها شي تلاتين سنة.
Well, it has been around thirty years.
تلاتين سنة... شلون التعليم عنكم؟
Thirty years... How is education here?
كويس.
Good.
نسبة التعليم عندكم كويسة؟
Is the education rate good here?
إي كويسة الحمدلله.
Yes it's good, thank God.
آخر سؤال، إنتو يعني مركزكم وين؟
Last question, where is your district center?
مركزكم شران، ولا عزاز، ولا وين؟
Is your center Sheran, or Azaz, or where?
مركزنا شران، ناحية شران.
Our center is Sheran, the Sheran sub-district.
إي، بس يعني لما بتروحوا بتشتروا وبتبيعوا وكذا؟
Yes, but I mean when you go to buy and sell and so on?
نشتري من عزاز أو من عفرين، يعني بس أكتر شي من عزاز.
We buy from Azaz or from Afrin, but mostly from Azaz.
لأنه باعتبارها قريبة علينا، منروح على عزاز.
Because considering it's close to us, we go to Azaz.
ولادكم وين بيكملوا دراسة؟
Where do your children continue their studies?
بيكملوا دراسة هلق، كان بعفرين، أو حلب، شايف كيف.
They continue their studies now, it used to be in Afrin, or
Aleppo, you see.
قديماً يعني هون بيدرسوا ابتدائي، بيروحوا ع عفرين بيكملوا
إعدادي وثانوي.
In the past, I mean, they would study primary here, they go
to Afrin to complete middle and high school.
إي هيك...
Yes, like that...
وبالأخير أولي هيك، أما هلق...
And finally, in the past it was like that, but now...
يعني حسب التيسير وين ما راح بيروح.
I mean, depending on the facilitation, wherever it goes, it
goes.
هو وين ما راح بيروح.
Wherever it goes, it goes.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health.
شكرا إلك.
Thank you.
الله يعافيك أستاذ، أهلا وسهلا.
May God give you health, sir, welcome.
يا مختار.
Oh Mukhtar.
خير عم ندور عليك بالضيعة وما لقيناك، إيش عم تسوي هون؟
Goodness, we were looking for you in the village and
couldn't find you, what are you doing here?
بقطف الكرم، الزيتون...
I'm harvesting the orchard, the olives...
شلونك سيدي؟
How are you, sir?
أهلا وسهلا، شرفتونا.
Welcome, you honored us.
أهلا وسهلا، تفضلوا.
Welcome, here you go.
الله يرزقك.
May God provide for you.
الله يسلمك، صحتين.
May God keep you safe, bon appetit.
هات سيدي شو نوع هالتين؟
Give me, sir, what kind of fig is this?
هاد التين، تين بلدي بيقولوله نحن طبعا بنزرعه على حواف
الطرقات هون عن الخير.
This fig, they call it local fig, of course we plant it on
the edges of the roads here for charity.
أهل الكروم هون يعني مشتهرين بهالأمر هاد، يعني اليوم إذا كان
عندك كرم على طريق...
The orchard owners here are famous for this, I mean today if
you have an orchard on a road...
بتحطلك تينة أو شجرة تين...
You plant a fig or a fig tree...
يعني للخير.
Meaning for charity.
أكيد للخير.
Definitely for charity.
إيش في أنواع للتين هون؟
What types of figs are here?
التين البلدي... عندنا المنشور، هلق في عندنا التين الموري
الأحمر، هاد البلدي الأصفر.
The local fig... we have the Manshour, now we have the red
Mouri fig, this is the yellow local one.
الضيعة بإيش مشهورة؟
What is the village famous for?
مشهورة بزراعة الزيتون، والتين والعنب وتربية المواشي طبعا
أستاذي.
It is famous for growing olives, figs, grapes, and raising
livestock of course, sir.
خلينا نمشي شوي، تفضل.
Let's walk a bit, please.
إيش أنواع الزيتون كمان اللي عندكم؟
What are the types of olives you also have?
في عندنا ثلاث أنواع أستاذي، في عندنا الزيتي البلدي نحن
بنقوله زيتي، وفي عندنا نوع بيقولوله الصوراني.
We have three types sir, we have the local Zayti we call it
Zayti, and we have a type they call Sourani.
إيوه.
I see.
وفي عندنا الخلخالي.
And we have the Khalkhali.
الخلخالي... هاد إيش نوعه هاد؟
The Khalkhali... what type is this one?
هاد الزيتي أستاذي.
This is the Zayti, sir.
هاد الزيتي. أنا ملاحظ لون التين هون كتير أخضر...
This is the Zayti. I notice the color of the fig here is
very green...
إي نعم، هاد أستاذي، هاد بلدي...
Yes indeed, this sir, this is local...
نعم.
Yes.
البلدي ضروري إنه يكون هيك يعني لونه هيك بيحافظ على لونه
هالنوع هاد.
The local one has to be like this, I mean its color like
this, this type preserves its color.
كم شجرة زيتون في عندكم بالضيعة هون يا مختار؟
How many olive trees do you have in the village here,
Mukhtar?
والله تقريبا شي 27 ألف شجرة زيتون.
Well, approximately twenty-seven thousand olive trees.
27 ألف شجرة زيتون؟ ما شاء الله، شي كويس. والعنب شلون؟
Twenty-seven thousand olive trees? As God willed, that's
good. And what about grapes?
العنب عندنا شي خمسة أو ست آلاف كرمة، طبعا في منهم ضمن حقول
الزيتون وفي منهم منفردات.
Grapes we have about five or six thousand vines, of course
some of them are within the olive fields and some are
separate.
في عندك البلاطة، العنب... في عندك البلاطة وفي عندك البلدي
اللي بنقوله نحن الدوكليجان.
You have the Balata, grapes... you have the Balata and you
have the local one we call Doklijan.
وفي عنا نوع الحمصي.
And we have the Homsi type.
الحمصي. الحبوب إيش في عندكم حبوب؟
The Homsi. Grains, what grains do you have?
الحبوب اللي عندنا أستاذي في عنا الحنطة، الشعير، السلة، بنزرع
الذرة... يعني الحمد لله من كل الأنواع.
The grains we have sir, we have wheat, barley, vetch, we
plant corn... I mean thank God from all types.
الحيوانات؟
Animals?
الحيوانات في عنا الماعز، مشهورة القرية طبعا بتربية الماعز
لأنه كون أنه تضاريس القرية صايرة جبلية.
Animals, we have goats, the village is famous of course for
raising goats because the terrain of the village is
mountainous.
يعني ما بيربى عندنا غير الماعز.
I mean nothing is raised here other than goats.
لكن اهتمام الناس، الأصل مصدر دخلهم هو الزراعة؟
But the people's interest, the main source of their income
is agriculture?
الزراعة وتربية المواشي.
Agriculture and raising livestock.
تربية المواشي.
Raising livestock.
الله يعطيك العافية.
Yes.
May God give you health.
أهلا وسهلا بك.
Welcome to you.
حياكم الله أستاذ مصطفى، أهلا وسهلا، شرفتونا.
A thousand thanks to you.
May God greet you Mr. Mustafa, welcome, you honored us.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
أهلا وسهلا.
Welcome.
شلونك عمو؟
How are you, uncle?
مية أهلا وسهلا.
A hundred welcomes.
شلون الصحة؟
How is your health?
الحمد لله.
Thank God.
نتعرف عليك؟
Can we get to know you?
الحمد لله.
Thank God.
نتعرف عليك؟
Can we get to know you?
أبو صطيف بيقولولي، عبد الحميد مصطفى.
They call me Abu Steif, Abdul Hamid Mustafa.
مية أهلا.
Oh, welcome to you.
A hundred welcomes.
هلق نحن وين نحن هون؟ هي المنطقة بيسموها الكرسانة مو هيك؟
Now where are we here? This area they call it Karsaneh,
right?
هي الكرسانة.
This is Karsaneh.
شو الكرسانة احكيلي عنها؟
What is Karsaneh, tell me about it?
هي الكرسانة من قديم من قديم إلها مقام.
This Karsaneh from a long, long time ago has a shrine.
كان العالم بيجوا بيزوروها.
People used to come and visit it.
بيذبحوا ذبائح.
They sacrifice sacrifices.
وهي هون محلها.
And here is its place.
وفي آثار هون في جب من قديم.
And there are ruins here, there is a well from the old
times.
وين المزار كان هون؟
Where was the shrine here?
Huh?
وين المزار كان هون؟
Where was the shrine here?
هون هي مزارتها هون عند الحجرات هدول.
Here, this is its shrine here by these stones.
هون في مغارة.
I see.
Here is a cave.
أيوة.
I see.
مغارة كانت قديمة.
A cave that was old.
وفي جب.
And there is a well.
جب هون؟
A well here?
آثار قديمة هي قديمة قدامنا.
Old ruins, these are old in front of us.
إي.
Yes.
هلق العالم كانت إيش تسوي تتبارك؟
Now, what did the people do to seek blessings?
العالم تيجي كانت تذبح ذبائح، تتبارك فيها...
People used to come and sacrifice sacrifices, seek blessings
in it...
المريض، الله الشافي، بيشفى وبيروح على بيته ماشي كان.
The sick, God is the healer, would be cured and walk home.
ووراك الجب هاد مبنيوها...
And behind you is this well they built...
نعم.
Yes.
هاد الجب.
This is the well.
نعم، هاد جب جمع؟
Yes, is this a collection well?
هاد جمع، من أولي ما بنعرف نحن، محفور، جمع جب، عميق يعني...
This is a collection well, from the old days we don't know,
dug, collection well, deep I mean...
هاد الجب.
This is the well.
هاد الجب عميق.
This well is deep.
نعم.
Yes.
ما حدا بيصل على أساسه.
No one reaches its bottom.
ومقبرة كأنه هون؟
And a cemetery it seems here?
هي مقابر كانت... أولي كنا نروح على زيارة النبي هوري، هلق عم
نجي لهون.
These were cemeteries... earlier we used to go to visit Nabi
Hori, now we are coming here.
لهون بتدفنوا موتاكم؟
Here you bury your dead?
إي هون، كانت المقام هون.
Yes here, the shrine was here.
هون المقام؟
Here is the shrine?
هون المقام.
Here is the shrine.
هاد قبل المدخل من هون...
This before the entrance from here...
كان شهيد مقام...
It was a martyr's shrine...
يعني فوق القبر ساووا قبة وصارت مقام؟
Meaning over the grave they built a dome and it became a
shrine?
إي مقبرة، وين كانت يجوا يناموا جنبها...
Yes a cemetery, where they used to come sleep next to it...
يذبحوا ذبائح، يدهنوا من ترابها، من دم اللي ذبحوه...
Sacrifice sacrifices, smear from its dirt, from the blood of
what they sacrificed...
بيدهنوا، بيناموا جنبها، وبيشافي الله. بيشفى.
They smear, sleep next to it, and God heals. He is cured.
وهداك الجرن هداك كانت فيه على طول فيه مي.
And that basin, that one always had water in it.
في جرن واضح إي.
There is a clear basin, yes.
الجرن على طول كان فيه مي. وهي الزيارة...
The basin always had water in it. And this visit...
يعني بيقولوا لها الكرسانة.
I mean they call it Karsaneh.
الكرسانة شو معناتها كرسانة؟
Karsaneh, what does Karsaneh mean?
كرسانة باسم مرة، باسم زلمة، ما بنعرف.
Karsaneh in the name of a woman, in the name of a man, we
don't know.
بس شو بتعني إيش بتعني الكلمة؟
But what does it mean, what does the word mean?
بتعني يعني مقام، وشهيد...
It means I mean a shrine, and a martyr...
أيوة. هدول أشجار سنديان هي مو هيك؟
I see. These are oak trees, right?
هاد سنديان.
This is oak.
وهونيك سنديان؟
And over there is oak?
هداك سنديان، هاد بلوط وبيصير كبار.
That is oak, this is acorn and it gets big.
بلوط.
Acorn.
كمان سمعت شغلة تانية يا عمو، إنه حتى كانوا يجيبوا حيواناتهم
لهون، يدوروها حول الكرسانة.
Also I heard another thing, uncle, that they even used to
bring their animals here, to walk them around Karsaneh.
نعم، أنا وصلتها، وجينا، وكتير ناس من الضيعة، كل اللي من
القرى بيجوا...
Yes, I reached it, and we came, and many people from the
village, all those from the villages come...
ليش بيجوا، ليش بيجيبوا حيواناتهم؟
Why do they come, why do they bring their animals?
حيوانات بيصير فيهم جرب، بيصير فيهم مرض، بيجوا بيدوروها
بيزوروها بهالمقام...
Animals get scabies, get sick, they come walk them, visit
this shrine...
بيذبحوا ذبائح، بيعملوا أكل، شرب...
They sacrifice sacrifices, make food, drink...
والعالم...
And the people...
بتأنس وتروح على بيتها.
Feel comforted and go home.
بيحتفلوا يعني هون؟
They celebrate here, I mean?
بيحتفلوا، هذا من قديم، قديم، قديم.
They celebrate, this is from old, old, old times.
قديم، وأنت وعيت على هالمسألة هي؟
Old, and you became aware of this matter?
أنا وعيت.
I became aware.
وإيمت توقفت هالعادة هي بطلت؟
And when did this custom stop, quit?
هالعادة هي بطلت، يعني بتعرف أنت... العالم كلها طحشت، طلعت
على حلب...
This custom stopped, I mean you know... all the people
rushed, went up to Aleppo...
تمت الختيارية بهون...
The elderly remained here...
يعني ما صار اعتناء كتير... وهلق ثانياتنا من جديد عم نبني
مقابرنا هون.
I mean there wasn't much care... and now secondly from anew
we are building our cemeteries here.
نعم.
Yes.
كنا نروح على النبي هوري، طريق بعيد وبيجي فيضان مي، والطريق
كان مقطوع...
We used to go to Nabi Hori, a far road and a water flood
comes, and the road was cut off...
هلق عملنا مقابر هون من جديد.
Now we made cemeteries here anew.
هاد المكان هون كله كان عبارة عن فسحة فيها بناء؟
This place here all was a courtyard with a building in it?
فسحة، هي فسحة ما كان حدا يفلحها ولا يزرعها، ولا واحد يحسن
يخرب عليها.
A courtyard, this is a courtyard no one used to plow it nor
plant it, and no one could ruin it.
بس فيها بناء كان؟
But it had a building?
لا. بس فيها مقابر.
No. But it has cemeteries.
مقابر.
Cemeteries.
مقابر قديمة.
Old cemeteries.
للضيعة بس؟
For the village only?
للضيعة.
For the village.
يعطيك العافية يا عمو.
May God give you health, uncle.
أهلين وسهلين، مية سلامة، أهلا وسهلا، الله يحييك... حلت
البركة فيكم.
Welcome, a hundred peaces, welcome, may God greet you...
blessings came upon you.
أعزائي المشاهدين، إلى هنا وتنتهي هذه الجولة التي قدمناها لكم
من قرية ميرساوا في ريف ناحية شران منطقة عفرين ريف حلب
الشمالي.
Dear viewers, here ends this tour that we presented to you
from the village of Mearsawa in the countryside of Sharran
sub-district, Afrin district, northern Aleppo countryside.
سنكون معكم في الأسبوع القادم في حلقة جديدة وقرية جديدة.
We will be with you next week in a new episode and a new
village.
إلى ذلك الوقت ننتظر منكم تعليقاتكم وآراءكم حول هذا البرنامج.
Until that time we await your comments and opinions about
this program.
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته.
Peace, mercy, and blessings of God be upon you.